{"tossups": [{"question": "In fluid dynamics, streamlines are vectors instantaneously tangent to those of this quantity. When drag and buoyant forces are equal to gravity, an object experiences the \u201cterminal\u201d variety of this quantity. The amount of this quantity required to overcome the force of gravity is known as the (*) \u201cescape\u201d variety. The rate of change of this quantity is acceleration. For 10 points, name this quantity often expressed as a speed combined with a direction.", "answer": "velocity [accept terminal velocity or escape velocity]", "subcategory": "Physics", "category": "Science"}, {"question": "H. pylori is a bacterium commonly found in this organ. This organ, which is the site of chief cells, also contains parietal cells that secrete intrinsic factor. Foveolar cells produce the mucus that lines the inner walls of this organ, which protect the tissue of this organ from (*) hydrochloric acid. Located between the esophagus and the small intestine is, for 10 points, what organ that digests food after it is chewed?", "answer": "stomach", "subcategory": "Biology", "category": "Science"}, {"question": "The relative form of this quantity is defined as the ratio of the partial pressure and equilibrium vapor pressure of water vapor. This quantity, which can be measured with a hygrometer, is maximized at the dew point. This quantity, which is often expressed as a percentage, is used alongside (*) temperature to calculate the heat index. For 10 points, name this quantity that indicates the likelihood of fog to be present, the concentration of water in the air.", "answer": "humidity [accept relative humidity]", "subcategory": "Other Science", "category": "Science"}, {"question": "In a play by this author, Samuel Parris discovers his daughter Betty dancing with the slave Tituba in the forest. In that play by this author, Giles Corey is tortured to death by pressing and Abigail Williams is accused of witchcraft. In another play by this author of The (*) Crucible, Linda, Biff, and Happy attend Willy Loman\u2019s funeral after he dies in a car crash. For 10 points, name this American playwright of Death of a Salesman.", "answer": "Arthur Miller [or Arthur Asher Miller]", "subcategory": "Drama", "category": "Literature"}, {"question": "This author claimed \u201cmusic hath a far more pleasing sound\u201d and \u201cCoral is far more red than her lips red\u201d in a poem mocking conventional romantic poetry that begins \u201cMy mistress\u2019 eyes are nothing like the sun.\u201d This author wrote \u201cThou art more lovely and more temperate\u201d in a (*) 14-line poem that begins \u201cShall I compare thee to a summer\u2019s day?\u201d For 10 points, what Elizabethan-era \u201cBard of Avon\u201d wrote 154 sonnets?", "answer": "William Shakespeare", "subcategory": "Poetry", "category": "Literature"}, {"question": "An author with this last name included poems like \u201cThe Swan\u201d and \u201cThe Albatross\u201d in his collection The Flowers of Evil. A fictional couple with this last name were members of the VFD and were the parents of a girl who ties her hair back in a ribbon to think. Count (*) Olaf is the main enemy of three children with this last name. For 10 points, give this last name of Violet, Klaus, and Sunny in Lemony Snicket\u2019s A Series of Unfortunate Events.", "answer": "Baudelaire [accept Charles Baudelaire; accept Baudelaire family or Baudelaires; accept Violet Baudelaire; accept Klaus Baudelaire; accept Sunny Baudelaire; prompt on Violet or Klaus or Sunny]", "subcategory": "Other Literature", "category": "Literature"}, {"question": "This politician requested that James K. Polk specify the \u201cspot\u201d where Mexicans spilled blood on American soil in his \u201cSpot Resolutions.\u201d In his Cooper Union address, this politician affirmed his opposition to expansion of slavery. This politician stated that \u201ca (*) house divided against itself cannot stand\u201d in a speech against Stephen Douglas. For 10 points, name this politician who, as president, issued the Emancipation Proclamation.", "answer": "Abraham Lincoln", "subcategory": "American History", "category": "History"}, {"question": "One king of this country imprisoned his mother, Joanna the Mad, and sponsored Magellan\u2019s circumnavigation of the globe. Another king of this country married Mary I of England and sent a large armada to that country to claim the English throne after her death. That king, (*) Phillip II, also became heir to the throne of Portugal during the Iberian Union. For 10 points, name this kingdom led from Madrid.", "answer": "Kingdom of Spain", "subcategory": "European History", "category": "History"}, {"question": "The Dutch were given special trading permissions at this country's artificial island of Dejima. Imperial leadership was reinstated after this country experienced the Boshin War. After \"Black Ships\" entered the harbor of this country's capital in 1853, this country signed the Treaty of (*) Kanagawa with the United States. For 10 points, name this country where the Tokugawa Shogunate once ruled.", "answer": "Japan", "subcategory": "World History", "category": "History"}, {"question": "During a failed coup d'\u00e9tat, this man attempted to put Erich Ludendorff in power. [M] For 10 points, name this man, who, after his arrest for his leadership in that Beer Hall Putsch, composed Mein Kampf from his prison cell.", "answer": "Adolf Hitler [E] Hitler was the leader of this far-right German political party, whose paramilitary branches included the SS and SA. This party also conducted the Holocaust during World War II. ANSWER: Nazi Party [accept NSDAP or the Nazis] [H] This Nazi Party member advocated for a style of \"total war\" when it became apparent that the Germans were going to lose World War II. He also served as the Minister of Propaganda under Hitler. ANSWER: Joseph Goebbels", "subcategory": "World History", "category": "History"}], "bonuses": [{"leadin": "These circuit components allow current to flow in only one direction. For 10 points each:", "answers": ["diodes", "battery", "capacitors"], "parts": ["Name these circuit components that can convert AC into DC and are common in modern lightbulbs in their \u201clight emitting\u201d type.", "This circuit component is used to provide a voltage difference to a circuit and are used in common devices in their AA (\u201cdouble-A\u201d) and AAA (\u201ctriple-A\u201d) varieties.", "These circuit components store charge, and their \u201cparallel plate\u201d type is the most simple; the voltage difference across one of these devices is equal to the charge stored on this device divided by its namesake property"], "subcategory": "Physics", "category": "Science"}, {"leadin": "This metal is added to steel to make stainless steel. For 10 points each,", "answers": ["chromium (accept Cr)", "nickel (accept Ni)", "mercury (accept Hg)"], "parts": ["Name this transition metal that is named after the Greek word for \u201ccolor\u201d and is the namesake of some green and yellow pigments.", "This other transition metal is one of the few metals that can exhibit ferromagnetism, and it is the namesake of the 5 cent coin in American currency, for which it makes up about 25%.", "This element, another transition metal, is the only metal that is in the liquid phase at standard room temperature, and this toxic element, also known as quicksilver, is commonly used in thermometers."], "subcategory": "Chemistry", "category": "Science"}, {"leadin": "One of the title characters of this novel uses the Great Seal of England as a nutcracker. For 10 points each:", "answers": ["The Prince and the Pauper", "Tom Sawyer [accept either underlined part]", "Mark Twain [accept Samuel Langhorne Clemens]"], "parts": ["Name this novel in which the peasant boy Tom Canty and the Prince of Wales Edward Tudor switch roles in society. Edward vows to reign with mercy and kindness in this novel after experiencing the peasant lifestyle.", "The author of The Prince and the Pauper also created this character. This character falls in love with Becky Thatcher and tricks other kids into whitewashing a fence for him.", "This American author who invented Tom Sawyer also described a trip down the Mississippi River in The Adventures of Huckleberry Finn."], "subcategory": "Long Fiction", "category": "Literature"}, {"leadin": "This poet\u2019s semi-autobiographical poem The Prelude was published posthumously. For 10 points each:", "answers": ["William Wordsworth", "daffodils [accept flowers]", "Lyrical Ballads"], "parts": ["Name this English Romantic poet. He claimed \u201cFive years have past; five summers, with the length / Of five long winters!\u201d in \u201cTintern Abbey,\u201d a poem written after a walking tour along the River Wye with his sister.", "Wordsworth\u2019s poem \u201cI Wandered Lonely as a Cloud\u201d is sometimes titled for one type of these objects and describes a \u201chost, of golden\u201d ones of these objects \u201cfluttering and dancing in the breeze.\u201d In that poem, the narrator\u2019s \u201cheart with pleasure fills / and dances with [these objects].\u201d", "Wordsworth co-authored this collection with Samuel Taylor Coleridge that marked the beginning of the Romantic movement in English literature."], "subcategory": "Poetry", "category": "Literature"}, {"leadin": "In a story by Jorge Luis Borges set in mythical Babylon, one of these luck-based events dictates every activity that takes place. For 10 points each:", "answers": ["a lottery", "stoning [accept lapidation]", "Shirley Jackson"], "parts": ["Name these events. In another story titled for one of these events first published in The New Yorker, the title event takes place on June 27th and Tessie Hutchinson draws the only marked piece of paper from a box.", "At the end of \u201cThe Lottery,\u201d Tessie dies in this manner by the hands of the townspeople. This form of capital punishment involves a group of people throwing rocks at the target until they die from blunt force trauma.", "This author received a large amount of criticism from the readers of The New Yorker in response to her story \u201cThe Lottery.\u201d This author also wrote the supernatural horror novel The Haunting of Hill House."], "subcategory": "Short Fiction", "category": "Literature"}, {"leadin": "Former secretary of state John Kerry claimed that this country was a \u201cnarco-kleptocracy.\u201d For 10 points each:", "answers": ["Republic of Panama", "George H. W. Bush", "canal"], "parts": ["Name this Central American country once led by Manuel Noriega that separated from Colombia in 1903. It was invaded by the United States in Operation Just Cause in 1989.", "This man ordered the invasion of Panama during his presidency. This man also negotiated NAFTA and presided over the First Gulf War. This Republican\u2019s son also became president in 2001.", "In 1977, the Trujillos-Carter Treaty agreed to give one of these structures back to the Panamanians. The Panamanian one of these structures connects the Pacific and Atlantic Oceans, allowing ships to avoid the long journey around South America."], "subcategory": "World History", "category": "History"}, {"leadin": "Despite being a Democrat, this president was supported by a group of Republican activists who took their name from the Algonquian term for \u201cwar leader.\u201d For 10 points each:", "answers": ["Grover Cleveland [accept Stephen Grover Cleveland]", "Pullman Strike", "New York State"], "parts": ["Name this president, whose victory in the election of 1884 was largely due to support from the Mugwumps. The Panic of 1893 began this president\u2019s second term, the only nonconsecutive term of any president.", "During his second term, Cleveland sent in troops to put down this 1894 strike based on his constitutional responsibility to have mail delivered. This railroad strike was led by Eugene V. Debs.", "Cleveland grew up in this state, where he began his political career before entering the presidency. Cleveland opposed the power of Tammany Hall in this state, where he previously served as the Mayor of its city of Buffalo."], "subcategory": "American History", "category": "History"}]}